Guide to the Percival L. Prattis Papers, 1916-1980 AIS.2007.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Percival L. Prattis Papers
1916-2011
1936-1964
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Prattis, Percival Leroy
AIS.2007.01
3.75 Linear Feet (3 boxes, 4 volumes)
This collection contains documents relating to the life and career of journalist, Percival L. Prattis, executive editor of the Pittsburgh Courier newspaper. The material dates between 1916 and 1980, with the majority of material dating from 1936 to 1964. The materials in this collection are correspondence, financial reports of the Courier, drafts of articles and stories, scrapbooks, and photographs.
Separated Material
The Pittsburgh Courier, Pittsburgh Edition issues that were a part of this collection have been separated out and retained for preservation. Please consult the ASC for further information.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following three series:
Series I. The Pittsburgh Courier, 1936-1969
Series II. Correspondence, 1935-1979
Series II. Personal, 1916-1980
Biography
Percival Leroy (P.L.) Prattis was born on April 27, 1895 in the Germantown section of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. He was the only son of Alexander and Ella (Spraggins) Prattis. He attended grade school at the Christiansburg Industrial Institute in Cambria (now Christiansburg), Virginia, from 1908 to 1912. For further education, he attended the Hampton Institute (now Hampton University) in Hampton, Virginia, from 1912 to 1915. He later graduated in 1916 from the Ferris Institute, which was a preparatory academy for low income children in Big Rapids, Michigan.
Prattis served in the U.S. Army during World War I. He was a Battalion Sergeant Major, headquartered in the Company 813 Pioneer Infantry. He was stationed in France from September 15, 1918 to July 13, 1919, and was honorably discharged from his duties on July 23, 1919.
P.L. Prattis began his career in 1919 as the editor of the newly formed Michigan State News in Grand Rapids, Michigan. In 1921 he moved to Chicago, Illinois, to become the city editor of the Chicago Defender, which was the most influential African American weekly newspaper in the country at the beginning of World War I. The Chicago Defender often used sensationalistic headlines and graphic images to capture the reader's attention and convey the horror of lynching and other atrocities affecting African Americans. It was the first African American newspaper to have a circulation over 100,000. Prattis held this position until May 1923. In June 1923 he was hired as the city editor of the Associated Negro Press in Chicago, which included articles that were syndicated by other African American newspapers. He also traveled on assignment and reported on international stories, such as the activities of the Moton Commission on Education in the Republic of Haiti; he even interviewed the Emperor of Ethiopia, Haile Selassie in England. He moved to Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, in 1936 to take a position with the highly influential African American newspaper the Pittsburgh Courier.
The Pittsburgh Courier, which was the leading African American newspaper by 1926, came from relatively inauspicious beginnings. The paper was founded by Edwin E. Harleston, a guard for the H.J. Heinz Company, as an outlet for his poetry. The first issue in 1907 was two pages in length and featured Harleston's poetry. Robert L. Vann, an attorney, drew up incorporation papers and assisted Harleston in finding investors. As one of the few African American lawyers in the city and a friend of Harleston, Vann was retained as legal counsel. Since the Courier could not afford to pay Vann, "he was given ten shares of stock valued at five dollars each in lieu of a fee" (Bunie, p. 44). Vann also was a regular editorial contributor to the Courier. In the fall of 1910 Edwin Harleston quit the paper due to creative differences and financial disagreements with the other investors. The remaining partners offered the editorship to Vann due to his experience as editor of The Courant, a student literary publication at the Western University of Pennsylvania (now the University of Pittsburgh). He was the Courier's editor, treasurer, and legal counsel and held these positions until his death in 1940.
The Pittsburgh Courier became a force for social change. Editorials by Robert Vann and others stressed that the policy of the Pittsburgh Courier was to "uplift of the Negro race…through the medium of the columns (Brewer, p. 24)." Editorials at the Courier called attention to improvements needed in housing, health care, education, job opportunities, political awareness, crime, Jim Crow, and misrepresentation in the white press. When Prattis was hired as a city editor in 1936, the Pittsburgh Courier was the most influential African American newspaper in the country, with a circulation over "250,000" (Bunie, p. 222). Prattis also had duties as reporter and was dispatched on international assignments to the Middle East, Far East and post-World War II Europe. During World War II, he traveled extensively covering the African American Armed Forces.
In 1947 he was unanimously granted membership in the Senate and House press galleries by the executive committee of the Periodical Correspondents Association, thus making him the first such permitted African American journalist. In 1948 he was promoted to managing editor, a position he held until 1956. While working at the Courier, Prattis also wrote the column "The Horizon," and was a correspondent for Our World magazine. He was named executive editor of the Pittsburgh Courier in 1956. During this time at the Courier, he highlighted the struggles of African Americans for fair employment opportunities from teaching positions to major league sports. In the 1960s the Pittsburgh Courier's circulation fell as the paper began to lose money and was no longer profitable. Many African American newspapers lost circulation during this time period as mainstream white newspapers gave coverage to the Civil Rights' Movement. Mr. Prattis retired from the Courier in 1965 after it was bought by John Sengstacke, publisher and owner of the Courier's longtime competitor, the Chicago Defender.
In retirement P.L. Prattis focused on community involvement and was very active in a number of organizations around Pittsburgh. He was the first African American officer on the Community Chest of Allegheny County Council; president of the Brashear Association; and vice-president of the Federation of Social Agencies of Allegheny County for six years. He sat on the boards of the Centre Avenue YMCA, the Pittsburgh branch of the N.A.A.C.P. and the Urban League. He was named "Community Leader of the Year" by the Jewish War Veterans Post 49. In 1962 he was awarded a medal as one of Hampton Institute's most illustrious alumni and in 1965 was given the "Master of Men" award by the state of Pennsylvania YMCA.
P.L. Prattis married Helen Marie Sands in 1939 and their daughter, Patricia, was born in 1943. Prattis died February 29, 1980 at the Veterans Administration Hospital in Aspinwall, Pennsylvania.
Sources used:
Bunie, Andrew. Robert L. Vann of the Pittsburgh Courier: Politics and Black Journalism. Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1974.
Brewer, James Howard. "Robert Lee Vann and the Pittsburgh Courier." Thesis University of Pittsburgh, 1941.
Previous Citation
Percival L. Prattis Papers, 1916-1980, AIS.2007.01, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Accruals
Additional material received in January 2011.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Patricia Prattis Jennings in December 2006.
Scope and Content Note
The Percival L. Prattis Papers contains correspondence, writings, and photographs from 1916 to 1980. The collection contains administrative and financial records of the Pittsburgh Courier. There are also materials related to his career after retirement from the Courier, including his personal and family life. Each series contains a scope note detailing the content found within the records.
In January 2011, Patricia Prattis Jennings, daughter of P.L. Prattis, donated additional materials. Included were professional and personal correspondence, photographs, and newspaper clippings. The new material has been added at the end of each existing series. Further scope notes are found after each series title.
Related Material
Brashear Association Records, 1891-1978, AIS.1979.17, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Frank E. Bolden Papers, 1930-1969, AIS.2008.05, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Community Chest of Allegheny County Records, 1933-1960, AIS.1968.14b, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), Pittsburgh Branch Records, 1964-1966, 1974, AIS.1964.38, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Urban League of Pittsburgh Records, 1915-1963, AIS.1981.11, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
The Percival Leroy Prattis Papers, 1916-1980, Personal Papers, Moorland Spingarn Research Center, Howard University
The Courier's Big Story: A Romance in Journalism, 1953, film: Can 599, 600, Cinecraft Productions films (Accession 2019.227), Audiovisual Collections and Digital Initiatives Department, Hagley Museum and Library, Wilmington, DE 19807
Newspapers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; African Americans -- Civil rights -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Courier (Pittsburgh, Pa.: City ed.); Courier (Pittsburgh, Pa.: National ed.); Courier (Pittsburgh, Pa.: Pacific Coast ed.); Courier (Pittsburgh, Pa.: Midwest ed.); Pittsburgh (Pa.); Correspondence; Financial records; Photographs; Social action; Memorabilia; Personal papers; Scrapbooks; African American journalists -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Journalists -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; African American newspapers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Vann, Jessie; Vann, Robert L.; Centre Avenue YMCA (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Frontiers International; Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Co.; Prattis, Percival Leroy
- The Pittsburgh Courier, 1936-2011; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains memos, financial reports and statements, story leads, and photographs created during Prattis' tenure at the Pittsburgh Courier and the period directly after, covering the years 1936 to 1969. It is further divided into five subseries: Administrative Materials, Financial, Photographs, Writings, and Recognition.
  - Administrative Materials, 1936-1967; 1.
    Administrative Materials are files that were created during Prattis' tenure at the paper. Prattis was very involved in the day-to-day operations of the Courier. He began as an editor in 1936 working his way from city editor to managing editor and later executive editor in 1948. Prattis retired from the Pittsburgh Courier in 1965 after it was bought by John Sengstacke, owner and publisher of the Chicago Defender. He also was a regular columnist for the paper. Included in this subseries are By-Laws of the Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company and various press passes granted to Mr. Prattis. There is also information on the trust of Mrs. Vann's estate and the management of the Pittsburgh Courier. Recently added material can be found under the section "New Material Added." The subseries are arranged chronologically by year.
    - Invitations and Press Passes, 1936, 1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - By-Laws of the Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper clippings regarding P.L. Prattis, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Press cards and Invitations from United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - U.S. State Department Credentials for United Nations Conference in San Francisco, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Assorted Pittsburgh Courier Materials, 1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Program for Birthday Testimonial in honor of Mrs. Robert L. Vann, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Our World Publishing Company, Inc., Resolutions adopted by the Board of Directors, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Publication of the Cleveland Courier, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Memos and Envelope Letterhead, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - P.L. Prattis Testimonial Banquet Program, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Petition to Terminate Trust of Estate of Jessie M. Vann, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Proposed Itinerary of P.L. Prattis, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letter from Robert L. Vann (half-page torn), undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - New Material Added, 2011
      - "Race Newsman (at long last) Admitted to Senate and House Press Galleries," clipping, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 69)
      - "Prattis' Column on Dr. DuBois Prompts Many Courier Readers to Pen Letters" clipping, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Financial, 1939-1964; 2.
    Scope and Content Note
    Included in the Financial subseries are copies of the Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company stock certificates issued to P.L. Prattis. Mr. Prattis had invested his own personal money into the paper and was committed to its success. As the newspaper entered the 1960s, it began to lose money and was no longer profitable. Prattis made a series of personal loans to keep the Pittsburgh Courier solvent. Of particular interest, are a series of cancelled checks Prattis wrote to the Pittsburgh Courier and Robert L. Vann's widow, Jessie, that document the loans. The Financial subseries is arranged chronologically by year and include comptroller's reports and financial statements that chart the fiscal health of the organization during this time period.
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Stock Certificates and List of Shareholders, 1939-1941, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Checks written by P.L. Prattis to Robert L. Vann Memorial Fund, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Checks written by P.L. Prattis to the Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company, 1941,1944,1946,1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Audit Report, March 31, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Resolution to Dispose of Our World Publishing Company Stock, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Shareholders of Our World Publishing Company Stock, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Our World Publishing Company Financial Report, October 31, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Checks written by P.L. Prattis to Jessie M. Vann, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Our World Publishing Company Stock Certificate, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Financial Report, May 31, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Financial Report, September 30, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Pittsburgh Publishing Company Financial Report, October 31, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Financial Report, November 30, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Comptroller's Office Report, January 1956 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Comptroller's Office Report, April 1957 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Legal Resolution with Marshall S. Leff for Financial and Management Control, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Comptroller's Office Report, January 1958 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Comptroller's Office Report, February 1958 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Comptroller's Office Report, March 1958 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Comptroller's Office Report, April-June 1958 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Comptroller's Office Report No. 9, September 14-19, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Comptroller's Office Report No. 10, September 26, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Balance Sheet, September 30, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Financial Report, December 31, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Financial Report, February 28, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Financial Report, June 30, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Balance Sheet, September 30, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Financial Statement, June 30, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Pittsburgh Courier Publishing Company Yearly Financial Statement, December 31, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Photographs, 1936-1961; 3.
    This subseries contains the photographs of P.L. Prattis taken while traveling on assignment for the Pittsburgh Courier. The subseries features images of the United States Armed Forces during World War II, which includes a photograph taken at a press conference with General George Marshall and Colonel Benjamin O. Davis. The Photographs subseries also features images of Prattis being honored at banquets, along with some photographs of Robert L. Vann, the Pittsburgh Courier's long-time editor, and his wife Jessie. Recently added material can be found under the section "New Material Added." The subseries is arranged by year with many images undated.
    - P.L. Prattis at Professional Events, 1936-1940s, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Organizing Committee of the War Bond Savings Club, ca.1942 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Blair House Press Conference for Edwin Barclay, President of Liberia, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - P.L. Prattis and Robert L. Vann with unidentified man, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - P.L. Prattis with African American Soldiers in Army Mess Hall, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - The Pittsburgh Courier's Frank Bolden as a War Correspondent, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Colonel Benjamin O. Davis, Sr., and Benjamin O. Davis, Jr., at Press Conference for African American Press, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - General George Marshall addressing the African American Press, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - P.L. Prattis and Jessie M. Vann with group, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - P.L. Prattis in group with President Eisenhower, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - P.L. Prattis in Tel Aviv, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - P.L. Prattis as speaker for National Insurance Convention, Durham, North Carolina, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Wilhelmina Butler, Jessie M. Vann, P.L. Prattis, Patricia Prattis, Ethel Ramos, and Paquita Harris, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Testimonial dinner in honor of P.L. Prattis, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Roy Wilkins and P.L. Prattis, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Lester Granger, Reba Schinault, and P.L. Prattis at Press Conference, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - P.L. Prattis at a shrine in Jerusalem, Israel, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - P.L. Prattis in Europe while on assignment for the Pittsburgh Courier, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - P.L. Prattis with unidentified men, undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - P.L. Prattis, Rev. Toliver, Dr. Eugene Younge, Jr., and two other unidentified men, undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - New Material Added, 2011
      - P.L. Prattis and unidentified man (possibly related to Community Chest and Councils of America), 1960s (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Writings, 1945-1969; 4.
    The Writings subseries features story leads and drafts of articles, notes, and journal entries. Prattis wrote for the Pittsburgh Courier and other publications during this time period. Recently added material can be found under the section "New Material Added." The subseries is arranged chronologically.
    - Journal entries for the United Nations Conference on International Organization in San Francisco, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Writings by P.L. Prattis while on assignment in India, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - "Statement to General Lucius D. Clay", 1949 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - "Issues: Good and Bad." Draft for article in Associated Negro Press, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Report on Courier Caravan, October 2- December 1957 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Draft of the Courier Church Supplement, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - "The People of the Earth: History Special for Children", 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Writing Assignment on Josephine Baker, undated (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Story Lead on Draft of Constitution of Latin-Bloc Countries, undated (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Book review on "The First Circle", undated (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - "Homewood- Brushton- Belmar Boomtown, '68", undated (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - "The Horizon," Writing Assignment from the ship Argentina, undated (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Writing Assignment on Gaston Monnerville from Paris, undated (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - "Must We Surrender?", undated (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - "Over the Shoulder History," Lead for Pittsburgh Courier series, undated (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - "Poverty of the Negro, Prosperity of the Whites", undated (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - Profile of Virginia Paris, undated (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - "Road to Freedom", undated (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - "Reference to Maso Tse", undated (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Story Lead on Wilkinsburg Coalition, undated (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Writing Assignment from Cairo, undated (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Writing Assignment from London, undated (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Writing Assignment from Paris, undated (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - "Peace Prospects in the Holy Land", undated (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - "Thirteen Years under Nazi Terror: as told to P.L. Prattis," Third and Final Drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - "Truth is Delight," Review for the Pittsburgh Courier, undated (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - Story Lead on the death of Jessie M. Vann, undated (Box 1, Folder 90)
    - Story Lead on Dr. Euguene Younge, undated (Box 1, Folder 91)
    - Untitled Writing, undated (Box 1, Folder 92)
    - United Nations International Conference, San Francisco, Scrapbook, 1945 (Box 1, Volume 1)
    - New Material Added, 2011
      - "The Horizon" newspaper clippings of column, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 72-73)
      - "Autobiography", fragmentary, undated (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Recognition, 2011; 5.
    - New Pittsburgh Courier Centennial, Program, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - New Pittsburgh Courier Centennial, P. L. Prattis Award [Glass Sculpture by Edward Kachurik], 2011 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1935-1979; II.
  The Correspondence series consists of letters written and received by P.L. Prattis. It is divided into two subseries, professional and personal.
  - Professional Correspondence, 1935-1979; 1.
    The correspondence in this subseries chronicles issues relating to Prattis' career at the Pittsburgh Courier and after his retirement his involvement with organizations such as Frontiers International, YMCA, and the Yorkfellows. Of particular interest is a folder of correspondence from famous people which contains a handwritten letter from Lena Horne in 1971. Also found in this subseries is a copy of a letter Prattis wrote to then Senator John F. Kennedy on August 18, 1950. The letter is regards to a previous meeting the two had and developing possible series of articles on Kennedy's efforts on behalf of African Americans. Recently added material can be found under the section "New Material Added." The correspondence is arranged by year.
    - Correspondence from Notable People, 1935-1979 (Box 1, Folder 93)
    - Correspondence regarding the financial situation of the Courier, 1950, 1958, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 94)
    - Correspondence, 1945-1954 (Box 1, Folder 95)
    - Correspondence, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 96)
    - Correspondence, January- July 1958 (Box 1, Folder 97)
    - Correspondence, August-December 1958 (Box 1, Folder 98)
    - Correspondence, 1959-1966 (Box 1, Folder 99)
    - Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 100)